<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sjtoussaint.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sjtoussaint.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-20T16:53:10+00:00</updated><id>https://sjtoussaint.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Simon Toussaint&apos;s personal website. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Janny Wurts</title><link href="https://sjtoussaint.github.io/blog/2026/wurts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Janny Wurts"/><published>2026-02-20T15:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-20T15:43:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sjtoussaint.github.io/blog/2026/wurts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sjtoussaint.github.io/blog/2026/wurts/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="intro">Intro</h2> <p>This is the first of (potentially several) blog posts, in which I reflect on things that strike my fancy. One goal in particular will be to connect two passions of mine, economics and fantasy literature. In this first post, I reflect on Janny Wurts’ <strong>The Wars of Light and Shadow</strong> (WoLaS from now on). I recently finished the final book, <em>Song of the Mysteries</em>, after restarting reading the series somewhere last year.</p> <p><strong> Spoilers from now on, be warned! </strong></p> <h2 id="summary">Summary</h2> <p>tWoLaS is an 11-book cycle mainly taking place on the planet of Athera, with main continent Paravia. This is a planet that (we learn throughout the books) has not originally been inhabited by humans; instead, it was first populated by dragons and later also by three special races called Paravians: unicorns, centaurs, and sunchildren. The Paravians are the centerpiece of this world’s history, for they were sent directly by Ath (God, if you will) to bring grace to the world. You see, these dragons had the nasty habit of running amok with their creative magic, which led to countless horrors and destructions, foremost among them several genocidal nightmare races destroying every living thing.</p> <p>An interesting feature of the setting is that, while it on first glance looks medieval, it is in fact a sci-fi setting. The prime human movers, the seven super-powerful sorcerers known as the Fellowship of the Seven, arrive on Athera over 10,000 years before the books start. Their arrival is caused by the dragons, who magically pull their spaceship on collision course, and subsequently transform these humans into immortal creatures with mind-boggling power. Their task? To use that power to protect Paravian survival at all cost.</p> <p>And so they do. Over thousands of years, they hunt the drakespawn to extinction. Interestingly, when the dragon imperative doesn’t bind them, they commit themselves to the Law of the Major Balance: a Paravian concept where no “no force of nature should be used without consent, or against the will of another living being”. Throughout the books, we see the sorcerers ask permission of every sentient being before engaging their power. In Wurts’ vision, not only humans or animals have sentience; so do plants and even inanimate matter. All that is, vibrates; consent is aligning the frequency of what you do to be in harmony with a being’s core resonance. Here we see Wurts’ devotion to music, something I will return to.</p> <p>After safeguarding the Paravians from the drakespawn, the Fellowship’s past comes back to haunt them: the remnants of mankind travel through space following thousands of years of catastrophic interplanetary conflict; conflict instigated in no small part because of the Big Weapon created by seven scientists now known as the Fellowship. Struck with remorse, the Fellowship ask the Paravians if mankind can settle on Athera, taking responsibility for their conduct. What follows is six thousand years of monarchy, where the kings (and the nobility) are those humans who last longest when exposed to the Paravians’ mystic presence. The royal bloodlines are all engineered by the Fellowship to have a dominant trait (justice, compassion, and so on). Ordinary humans live in towns and cities, while the wilds remain proscribed. Technology remains forcibly limited to medieval standards; some humans’ attempts to discover gunpowder get them expelled to a splinter world.</p> <p>This comes back to haunt the Fellowship, since the experimenters’ offspring eventually create a technology that traps live spirits in mist fields. When the mist fields spiral out of control, this entity swallows their entire world, devours everyone’s spirit in the process, and oozes back towards Athera to smother that world too. At the same time, a conspiracy of necromancers and the Koriani (the Fellowship’s prime antagonists, more on which later) overthrows the monarchies, resulting in chaos and extermination of the noble clans. In utter chaos, descendants of the royal bloodlines are smuggled to another splinter world. The Paravians leave the mist-cloaked continent to an unknown location, leaving the understaffed Fellowship to manage affairs.</p> <p>Centuries later, two of the royal heirs, Lysaer s’Ilessid and Arithon s’Ffalenn, return to Athera and are swept up by the Fellowship. Their power manages to disperse the Mistwraith, restoring sunlight. However, the wraith’s counterstroke curses the two half-brothers to seek to destroy each other whenever they meet. Arithon, being mage-trained, has some control over the curse, but Lysaer succumbs wholesale. Over the next centuries, events spiral out of control, with wholesale war and small-scale tragedy marring Paravia’s surface. Along the way, the dragons and Paravians eventually return to our attention, the Fellowship is restored to its full strength, and at the very end, the Mistwraith is defeated; even if not all its evil has been undone.</p> <h2 id="assessment">Assessment</h2> <p>TWoLaS is an epic fantasy cycle, on the scale of grandeur of a Wheel of Time or Stormlight Archive. The plot spans centuries (with elaborate backstory going back tens of thousands of years), yet remains tightly knit and focused on a core set of characters. The magic is expansive and rich yet never feels contrived or mechanical; I am impressed with how naturally she merges the magical mechanics with her conception of the world and the story. The human tragedy in these stories is very compelling to me. At multiple points in the books I got almost physically unwell because of the agony suffered by Arithon and his friends, or because of Lysaer’s sly duplicity, or the Koriani cruelty.</p> <p>That said, the books are not easy to digest. This is partly because of its greatest strength: everything is tightly plotted, from start to finish. There is no meandering here; every action from the very first results in a very natural flow of consequences, such that the series reads as the natural unfolding of a very tight beginning. However, this also means that the plot develops slowly, and can even seem repetitive. On Reddit, I found <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Fantasy/comments/1ohguuu/comment/nlo0iga/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button">this funny comment</a> which captures this feeling (if a bit harshly):</p> <blockquote> <p>As I begun each installment of these novels: Narrator: What dastardly plot will the Koriathain order have this week (novel) to entrap Arithon, who will narrowly escape their evil clutches?? As I ended each novel: “We’ll get you next time Arithon!”, the Koriathain witches cackled as he rode into the sunset. I enjoyed the books but they felt like flowery novelizations of Inspector Gadget episodes.</p> </blockquote> <p>Ultimately, I think the <em>concepts</em> explored in the series are perhaps more compelling than the characters themselves. With that in mind, let’s get to the analysis.</p> <h2 id="analysis">Analysis</h2> <p>I will focus in my analysis on two themes: technology and progress, and Wurts’ conception of magic and music.</p> <h3 id="technology-and-human-progress">Technology and Human Progress</h3> <p>I write this review from the Netherlands, a country where the horrors of polio and cholera are still within living memory yet feel incredibly distant. In the course of the twentieth century, we have managed to improve wellbeing by a staggering amount. Let me be clear: this is a victory for progress through technological change. Yet the flip side of technology is also clear: the same science that brought us improved treatment for cancer also forms the basis for nuclear weapons; our understanding of DNA can both cure disease and be used to foster eugenics. What matters, therefore, is not just technological progress per se but its direction, <a href="https://economics.mit.edu/sites/default/files/2023-06/Distorted%20Innovation%20-%20Does%20the%20Market%20Get%20the%20Direction%20of%20Technology%20Right.pdf">as forcefully argued by Daron Acemoglu</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fantasy-economics"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="economics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In which I open the secret blog project with reflections on *The Wars of Light and Shadow*]]></summary></entry></feed>